<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ordenarye for all faythfull Chrystiãs to leade a vertuous and Godly lyfe here in this vale of miserie / translated out of Doutche into Inglysh by Anthony Scoloker. A Right goodly rule howe all faithfull Christians shall occupie and exercise them selves in their daily prayers</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5199.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">28678739</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 28678739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1873:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Ordenarye for all faythfull Chrystiãs to leade a vertuous and Godly lyfe here in this vale of miserie / translated out of Doutche into Inglysh by Anthony Scoloker. A Right goodly rule howe all faithfull Christians shall occupie and exercise them selves in their daily prayers</title>
                  <author>Scoloker, Anthony, fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker, Dwellyng in . S. Nycholas Paryshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Ippeswych,</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A right goodly rule" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: signatures G², G³, G⁶, G⁷ lacking. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸, H².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:1"/>
                  <p>The ordena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Rye for all faythfull Chryſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to leade a vertuous and Godly lyfe here in this vale of miſerie.</p>
                  <p>¶Tranſlated out of Doutche into In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſh by Anthony Scoloker.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>¶i. Cor. vij. ¶</bibl> Let euerie one abyde in the calling wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is called.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at Ippeſwych / by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryſhe.</p>
                  <p>Anno. 1548.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.¶</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:3"/>
                  <head>To the chriſten Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aule (good Chriſten rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fyrſt to Timothe the ſeconde chapter / ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our great graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother Eue / who after that ſhe was deceaued and ſubdued vnto the tranſgreſſyon / brought forth death vppon all her poſterite) decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth / that to heale ſo great a wounde / and to appeare beautifully in the eyes of the mightie Lorde whoſe dere ſonne Ieſus Chriſt ſayde.<note place="margin">2. Timo. 2.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 27.</note> Father thoſe that thou haſt geuen vnto me I will that where I am they be alſo with me / that they maye ſee my glorie. After the firſt rudiment of a Chrſtian (the which is faith) iij waytyng virgins / ought to be attendaunt ande ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable vnto him / that in this vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to leade a parfect life / Loue holines and diſcretion. Vnder the which diſcretion (as it maye be gathered by the properte of the Greke terme i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place) are compriſed chaſtite / temperaunce / mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſté
<pb facs="tcp:27933:4"/> and dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhame faſtnes / becauſe all theſe vertues are alwayes coherent ande Ioined to gether.<note place="margin">ſophroline</note> And holines / like as ſhe requireth to flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all vice / ſo doth ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the exerciſe of all vertuous workes and doinges that procede effectually fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith / thorowe loue. That the name of him maye be ſanctified who ſayde vnto his father. I haue declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / thy name. And will declare it / that the loue wherwith thou haſt loued me / maye be in them and I in them.<note place="margin">Ioan. 15.</note> Wherfore that by loue / the duetie of all men from the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt to the higheſt maye be knowen from the one to the other / reade ouer this lytle booke / that (walkinge in the daungerous patthes of this exile) thou mayeſt knowe howe to be trained vnto the manſyon place / prepared vnto the rightuous that neuer ſhall haue ende.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:4"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe the ſpirituall Prelates ought to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the Comune People.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde / I ſende you forth as ſhepe amonge wolues.<note place="margin">Math. 10. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Go ye your waye ande teach all nations and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe them in the name of the father / and of the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the holighooſt.<note place="margin">Math. 27. c</note> And teache them
<pb facs="tcp:27933:5"/> to kepe all thinges / what ſoeuer I haue commaunded you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 15. b. Col. 1. a.</note>Yea haue not choſen me / but I haue choſen you / and ordeined you / that ye go / and bringe forth frute.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn 25. c. Act. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. and 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>And ye ſhall beare me witnes / not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but alſo through oute the lande of Iury / and Samaria / and to the vttermuſt coaſtes of the earth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ioan. 20. c.</note>Receyue the holyghooſt. Whoſe ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſoeuer ye remit / they are remitted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ande whoſe ſynnes ſoeuer ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine / they are retained.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 18. b. Math. 16. c.</note>Verely I ſaye vnto you what ſoeuer ye ſhall binde vppon earth / ſhalbe bounde alſo in heauen / and what ſoeuer ye lowſe vppon earth / ſhalbe lowſed alſo in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Act. 20. d.</note>Take hede vnto your ſelues / and to all the flocke / amonge the whiche the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghooſt hath ſet you to be Byſſhoppes / to fede the congregation of God / whiche he hath purchaſed with his owne bloude.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. a.</note>Ieſus chriſt which came downe from heauen / ande is gone vp againe aboue all heauens to fulfyll all / hath ſet ſome to be Apoſtles / ſome to be Prophetes / ſome to<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. c.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:27933:5"/> be Euangeliſtes / ſome to be ſhepheardes and teachers / wherby the ſaintes might be coupled together / thorowe come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to the edefying of the body of Chriſt. A Biſſhoppe muſt be blameleſſe.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. a. Leuit. 21. b. Ezec. 44. d. Tet. 3. b.</note> The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of one wife ſober / diſcrete / manerlie / harberous / apte to teache / not geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wine / no fyghter / not geuen to fylthy lucre / but gentle abhorring ſtryfe / abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conuetuouſnes / and one that ruleth his owne houſe honeſtlie / hauing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t children with all honeſtie. For yf he can not rule his owne houſe / howe ſhall he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for the congregation of God?</p>
                     <p>The ſeruaunt of the lorde ought not to ſtriue / but to be gentle vnto euerye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / apte to teache / one that can forbeare the euell / one that can with mekenes enforme them that reſyſt / if God at any tyme wyll giue them repentaunce for to knowe the trueth / and to turne againe from the ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the deuell / which are holden in pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of hym / at his wyll.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. c. Gal. 6. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Preach the woorde / be feruent be yt in<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. a</note> ſeaſon or oute of ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Improue / rebuke / exhorte wyth all longe ſufferynge a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.
<pb facs="tcp:27933:6"/> For the tyme wyll come / whan they ſhall not ſuffere wholſome doctrine / but after theyr owne luſtes ſhall they (whoſe eares ytche) get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an heape of teachers / and ſhall turne theyr eares from the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth / and ſhalbe geuen vnto fables. But watch thou in all thinges / ſuffer aduerſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / do the worke of a preacher of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / fullfyll thyne offyce vnto the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 27. c. Ioh. 10. a</note>See that thou knowe the nombre of thy cattell / and loke well to thy flokes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Tito. 1. .b</note>A Byſſhoppe muſt cleaue faſte vnto the true woorde of doctrine / that he maye be able to exhorte with wholſome learning / and to improue them that ſaye againſt it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. c. Act. 5. c. Act. 20. d.</note>The Elders which are among you I exhorte / whiche am alſo an Elder / ande a witnes of the affliction in Chriſte / ande partaker of the glory that ſhalbe opened. Fede Chriſtes flocke which is amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you / ande take the ouerſyght of them / not as though ye were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled therto / but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie / not for the deſyre of fylthy ſucre / but of a good minde / not as though ye we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re lordes ouer the paryſſhens / but that ye<note place="margin">Tit. 2. a.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:27933:6"/> be an enſample to the flocke.</p>
                     <p>Who ſoeuer wilbe great amonge you / let hym be your miniſter / and who ſoeuer wilbe chefe let hi be your ſeruaunt.<note place="margin">Mat. 20. a.</note> Euen like as the ſonne of man came / not to be ſerued but to do ſeruice / and to gyue hys life to a redemption for many.<note place="margin">Mat. 10. a.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Go and preache the Goſpell / ſayinge. The kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is at hande. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le the ſycke / clenſe the lepers raiſe the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / caſt out the deuelles. Frelie ye haue receiued / frely giue againe.</p>
                     <p>Who is nowe a faithfull ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me his Lorde hath made ruler ouer his houſholde / that he maye geue them meate in due ſeaſon?<note place="margin">Mat. 24. a. Mat. 25. b.</note> Bleſſed is that ſeruaunt / whome his lorde (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he commeth) ſhall fynde ſo doinge / verelye I ſaye vnto you / he ſhall ſect him ouer all his goodes.<note place="margin">Apoc. 16. c.</note> But and if the euell ſeruaunt ſhall ſaye in hys harte Tuſh it wilbe longe or my lord co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beginne to ſmite his fellowes / yea / and to eate and drinke with the dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the ſame ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes lord ſhal come in a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye / whan he looketh not for him / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in an houre that he is not ware of / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
<pb facs="tcp:27933:7"/> him in peces / and giue him his rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with ypocrites / where ſhalbe waiting and gnaſſhing of tethe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ezech. 33. b</note>I haue made the a watchman vnto the houſe of Iſraell / that where as thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt any thinge oute of my mouthe / thou maiſt warne them on my behalfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">ij. Para. xix</note>See that ye do thus in the feare of the lorde / and faithfully in a parfet harte / In all cauſes that come vnto you from your bretheren (whiche dwell in their Cities) betwene bloude and bloude / betwene la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / betwene ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ordenaunces ye ſhall enforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſynne not againſt the lorde / and ſo the wrath to come vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you and youre bretheren.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note>Poſſeſſe neyther golde nor ſiluer. For the labourer is worthy of his rewarde. Go not from houſe to houſe. And into what ſoeuer citie you entre / and they receaue you eate ſoche thinges as are ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:7"/>
                     <head>Howe the Comen People ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe and behaue them ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the ſpyrituall Prelates.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>Let euery man this wyſe eſteme vs / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the miniſters of Chriſte / and ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of the ſecretes of God.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. a 2 Cor. 6 a Deu. x ix Iere. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> c</note> Nowe is there no more required of the ſtewardes, then that they be founde faithfull.</p>
                     <p>Humble thy ſoule vnto the elder / and bowe downe thy heade to a man of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. iiij. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:8"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccli. 7. d. Deut. 12. c. Num 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. d. and c.</note>Feare the lorde with all thy ſoule / and honoure his miniſters / loue thy maker with all thy ſtrength / and forſake not his ſeruauntes. Feare the lorde with all thy ſoule / and honoure his prieſtes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. Tim. 5. c.</note>The Elders that rule well / are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honoure / mooſt ſpecyally they which labour in the worde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge.<note place="margin">Deut. 25. a. 2. Cor. 9. b. Mat. 10. a.</note> For the ſcripture ſayeth. Thou ſhalt not moſell the mouth of the oxe that treadeth oute the corne. And the labourer is worthy of his rewarde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. b Gal. 5. a. 2. Tim. 5. b</note>We beſeke you brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that ye knowe them whiche laboure amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge you / and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ouerſyght of you in the lorde / ande geue you exhortacion / that ye haue them the more in loue / for theyr woordes ſake / and be at peace with them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Hebr. 13. a.</note>Remembre them which haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyght of you / whiche haue declared vnto you the worde of God. The ende of who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe conuerſacion / ſee that ye loke vppon / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d followe their faith. Obey them / and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for they watch for your ſoules / euen as they that muſt giue accountes therfore.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:8"/>
                     <p>Who goeth a warrefare at any time / vppon his owne wages?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.</note> Who planteth a vinyarde / and eateth not of the frute ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Who fedeth a flocke / and eateth not of the milk of the flock?<note place="margin">Rom. 15. d. Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. a.</note> If we haue ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you ſpiritual thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / is it a great thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g if we reape your bodelie thynges? But if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be partakers of this power on you / wherfore are not we rather? Knowe ye not that they which labour in the temple / haue theyr liuing of the temple? And they that waite at the aulter / enioie the aulter? Euen thus alſo hath the lorde ordeined / that they which preach the Goſpell / ſhuld liue of the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Mat. 10. a.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ezechias commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the people that dwelt at Ieruſalem / that they ſhulde giue porcions of theyr goodes vnto the prieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / that they might the more ſtedfaſtlye endure in the lawe of the lorde.<note place="margin">2. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>If a matter be to harde for the in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement / betwene bloude ande bloude / betwene plee ande plee / betwene ſtroke and ſtroke.<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> Thou ſhalt ryſe / and go to the prieſtes / the leuites / and to the Iudge which ſhalbe at that time / and ſhalt axe of
<pb facs="tcp:27933:9"/> them / and they ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l ſhewe the howe to iudge / and thou ſhalte doo therafter / as they ſaye vnto the. And if any man deale preſumptuouſlie / ſo that he harkeneth not vnto the prieſt (which ſtandeth to do ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto the lord thy god) or to the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / the ſame ſhall die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe the Wordlie and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour powers / as Emperour / Kinges / Princes / Iudges and Rulers ought to liue with theyr ſubiectes.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:9"/>
                     <p>Heare (Oye Kinges) and vnderſtand.<note place="margin">Sapi. vj. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> O learne ye that be Iudges of the endes of the earth / giue care / ye that rule the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titudes / and delite in moche people.<note place="margin">Rom. xiij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> For the power is geuen you of the lorde / and the ſtrength from the higheſt / which ſhall trye your workes / ande ſearch oute your Imaginacions / howe that ye / being offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his kingdome / haue not executed true iudgement / haue not kepte the lawe of ryghtuouſnes / nor walked after the wyll of God.</p>
                     <p>A Kynge ſhall not haue many horſes / neither ſhall he haue many wiues / neither ſhall he gather him ſiluer ande Golde to moche.<note place="margin">Deut. xvij.</note> He ſhall not lift vp his harte abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his bretheren / and ſhall not turne a ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de from the commaundementes of God / neither to the right hand nor to the lifte hande.</p>
                     <p>Mercy and faithfulnes preſerue the Kinge / ande with louinge kindenes his ſeate is holden vp.<note place="margin">Pro. xx. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſeate of the kinge that faithfullye iudgeth the poore / ſhall continue ſure for euermore.<note place="margin">Pro. xxix. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:10"/>
                     <p>Like as a roaringe lion and an hungrie beare / euen ſo is an vngodlie prince ouer the poore people. Where the prince is without vnderſtanding / ther is great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſyon and wronge. But if he be ſoche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as hateth couuetuouſnes / he ſhall lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge raigne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e. 2. a. Deut. 17. d. Ierem. 5. a. Pſal. 132. a.</note>Heare o ye heades of the houſe of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ye leaders of the houſe of Iſraell. Shulde not ye knowe what were laufull and right? But ye hate the good / ande lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the euell / ye plucke of mens ſkinnes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the fleſh from their bones.<note place="margin">Iere. 22. a. and 21. d. Zachar 7. b and 8. c.</note> Kepe equitie and rightuouſnes / deliuer the oppreſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of the violent / do not greue nor oppreſſe the ſtraunger / the fatherleſſe nor the widdowe / and ſheade no innocent bloude in this place.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. a. Ezay. 37. c.</note>Be wiſe nowe therfore (O ye Kinges) be warned ye that are iudges of the earth. Serue the lord with feare / ande reioyce before hym with reuerence. Kiſſe the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne leaſt the lorde be angrie / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo ye periſh from the ryght waye.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 1. a 3. Reg. 3. a.</note>O ſet your affection vppon wyſdome / ye that be Iudges of the earth.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:10"/>
                     <p>Make no labour to be made a Iudge / excepte it ſo were that thou couldeſt migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telie put downe wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">Eccle. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. a Iob. ix. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>d c Luk. xix b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take hede ye Iudges what ye doo / for ye execute not the iudgement of man / but of the lorde.<note place="margin">ij. Par. xix.</note> And he is with you in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therfore let the feare of the lord be with you / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beware / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d do it for with the lorde oure God there is no vnrightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes nor reſpect of parſones / nor accepting of giftes.</p>
                     <p>In iudgement be mercyfull vnto the fatherles as a father / ande be in ſteade of an huſband vnto their mother.<note place="margin">Eccle. iiij. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>With true Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the King ſetteth vp the lande / but if he be a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that taketh giftes / he turneth it vpſid downe.<note place="margin">Pro. xxix. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be no accepter of parſones / neither be deſyrous of giftes for they make wyſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blinde / ande chaunge the wordes of the rightuous.<note place="margin">Deut. xvij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that hath reſpect of pariones in iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement doth not well / and why?<note place="margin">Pro. xxviij.</note> He wyll do wronge / yea euen for a pece of bread.</p>
                     <p>A wiſe iudge wil ordre his people with diſcretion / and where a man of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:27933:11"/> beareth rule / there goeth it well. As the iudge of the people is him ſelfe / euen ſo are his offycers / and loke what maner of man the ruler of the citie is / ſoche are they that dwell therin.<note place="margin">Pro. xxix. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. xvij. d Apoc. xxiij a</note>The vngodlie taketh giftes oute of the boſome to wraſte the waies of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Exod. xxiij.</note>Thou ſhalt not wraſt the right of thy poore in his cauſe. Kepe thy farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe matters.<note place="margin">Suſan. viij Deut. xvij.</note> The innocent and rightuous ſhalte thou not ſlea. Thou ſhalt take no giftes / for giftes blinde euen them that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſharpe of ſighte / ande wraſt the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous cauſes.<note place="margin">Eecl. xx. d</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Leu. xxiiij. Ezay. v. e Prou iij. a Deut. xvij. Ezec. xiiij.</note>Curſed is he that wraſteth the right of the widdowe. Wo vnto them that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men to ſuppe oute wine and experte to ſet vp dronkennes. Theſe gyue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce with the vngodly for rewardes / but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne the iuſte cauſe of the rightuous.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ezay. x. a Luk. xij. f Mat. xxiiij.</note>Wo be vnto you (o ye Iudges) that make vnrightuous lawes / ande deuyſe thynges whiche be to harde for to kepe / wher thorow the poore are oppreſſed on euery ſyde / and the innocentes of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / are therwith robbed of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that
<pb facs="tcp:27933:11"/> widdowes maye be youre praye / and that ye maye robbe the fatherles.<note place="margin">Eſa. xxviij</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou be made a ruler / pride not thy ſelfs therin / but be thou as one of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">Eccl. 32. a Deut. xvij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let him that ruleth be diligent.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>na. xij. b</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe ſubiectes ſhall behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues towardes theyr ſuperiours and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rulers.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:12"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Exod xxij. Act. xxiij. a</note>The rulers of the People ſhalt thou not blaſpheme.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. xxiiij. and xx. a</note>Feare the lorde and the kinge / and kepe no companie with the ſlaunderous / for their deſtruction ſhall come ſodenlye.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Timo. ij.</note>Praye for kynges and Rulers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Tito. iij. a Rom. iv. a i. Petr. ij. a</note>Warne the people that they ſubmite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues vnto Princes / ande to the higher auctoritie and to obeye the offycers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Petr. ij. a</note>Submitte your ſelues vnto all maner ordenaunce of men for the Lordes ſake / whether it be vnto the kinge / as vnto the chefe heade / or vnto Rulers / as vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſent of him for the puniſhment of euell doers / but for the praiſe of them that do well.<note place="margin">Tito. iij. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. xiij. a</note>Let euery ſoule ſubmitte hym ſelfe to the auctorite of the hygher powers. For there is no power but of God.<note place="margin">Sap vi. a i. Petr. a. b</note> The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers that be / are ordeined of God / ſo that who ſoeuer reſyſteth the power / reſyſteth the ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>naunce of God. And they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſte ſhall receyue to them ſelues dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. For rulers are not to be feared for good woorkes but for euell.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. xiij.</note>And the ruler beareth not the ſwearde
<pb facs="tcp:27933:12"/> for nought. For he is the miniſter of God a taker of vengeaunce / to puniſh him that doth euell / Wherefore ye muſt nedes obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye / not onely for punyſhment but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. For this cauſe muſt ye giue tribute alſo. For they are Gods my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters / which maintaine the ſame defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.<note place="margin">Rom. xiij. b Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Giue to euery man therfore his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / tribute / to whome trybute belongeth / cuſtome to whome cuſtome is due / feare / to whome feare belongeth / honoure / to whome honoure pertaineth.</p>
                     <p>Geue vnto the Emperour / that which is the Emperours.<note place="margin">Mat xxij. c Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vij. d Rom. xiij. d</note> And giue vnto God / that whych is Gods.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe parentes / as father and mother / ought to rule and brynge vp theyr Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the feare of the lorde.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:13"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. vij. c and c. a</note>If thou haue ſonnes / bringe them vp in nurtoure and learning / and holde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in awe from theyr youth vp. If thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue doughters / kepe theyr body / and ſhewe not thy face cherefull towarde them.</p>
                     <p>Marie thy doughter / ande ſo ſhalte thou perfourme a weightie mater / but giue her to a man of vnderſtandinge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. 30.</note>Who ſo loueth hys childe / holdeth him ſtyll vnder correction / that he maye haue
<pb facs="tcp:27933:13"/> Ioye of him afterward.<note place="margin">Prou. 23. e and 23. Deu. vj. e.</note> He that teacheth his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / ſhal haue ioy of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nedeth not to be aſhamed among his acquaintaunce. Who ſo enformeth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d teacheth his ſonne / greueth the ennemy / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d before frendes he maye haue ioye of him. If thou dye yet arte thou as though thou were not dead / for thou haſt left one behinde the / that is lyke vnto the. An vntamed horſe wylbe harde / and a wanton childe wilbe wilfull. If thou bring vp thy chylde dylycatelye / he ſhall make the afrayd / and if thou pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye with hym / he ſhall bringe the to he auy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Laugh not with him / leaſt thou we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe with him alſo / and leaſt thy teeth be ſet on edge at the laſt.</p>
                     <p>If thy doughter be wanton / kepe her ſtrayghtlye / leaſt ſhe cauſe thine enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes laughe the to ſcorne / and the whole citie to giue the an euel reporte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo thou be faine to heare thy ſhame of euery man.<note place="margin">Eccl. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Eccl. 26. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not holde thy doughter to whoredome / that the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fal not to who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redom / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d waxeful of wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">Leuit. 29.</note> If thy
<pb facs="tcp:27933:14"/> doughter be not ſhamefaſte / holde hee ſtrayghtly / leaſt ſhe abuſe her ſelf thoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we ouermoch lyberté. Beware of all the dyſhoneſtie of hereyes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. xxiij Num. xxv. Deu xxij. c Mich. 1. b Eccle. xxij.</note>There ſhalbe no whoore amonge the doughters of Iſraell / neither whoreke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per amonge the doughters of Iſraell.</p>
                     <p>A miſnurtered ſonne is the diſhonour of the father. A foliſh doughter ſhalbe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regarded. And ſhe that commeth to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſte bringeth her father in heauynes. A doughter that is paſte ſhame / dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth both her father and her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Colloſ. iij. c</note>Ye fathers / rate not your children / leaſt they be of a deſperate minde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. xiij. c Pſal. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iij. Hebr. xij. b Pſal. xxxiii. Ephe. vi. a</note>He that ſpareth the rodde / hateth hys ſonne / but who ſo loueth him / holdeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer in nurtoure.</p>
                     <p>Ye fathers / prouoke not your children vnto wrath / but bring them vp in the nur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure and information of the lorde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou xxiij. and xiij. c Eccl. xxx. a</note>Witholde not correction from the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for if thou beateſt hym with the rodde / he ſhall not dye therof. Thou ſmiteſt him with the rodde / but thou delyuereſt his ſoule from helle.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:14"/>
                     <p>Let the elder men be ſober honeſt / dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete / ſounde in the fayth in loue / in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience.<note place="margin">Tito. ij. 2</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let the olde wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhewe them ſelues as it becommeth holynes / that they be no falſe accuſers / not geuen to moche wyne / that they teache honeſt thinges / that they enforme the yong women to be ſobermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / to loue theyr huſbandes / to loue their chyldren / to be diſcrete / chaſte / huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiflye / good / obedient vnto theyr huſbandes that the worde of God be not euell ſpoken of.<note place="margin">Geneſ. iij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Let the yongmen lykewyſe be ſober.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe youth ſhall obey their elders / honouring them in the feare of the lorde.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:15"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">epheſ. vj. a Colloſ. iij. exod. 20. b</note>Ye childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obeye your elders in the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / for that is right. Honoure thy father / and thy mother / that is the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that hath any promys / that thou maiſt proſper a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lyue longe vppon earth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Tito. jj. a</note>Lett the yongemen be ſobermynded.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i Petr. ij.</note>Ye yonger ſubmitte your ſelues vnto the Elder.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">eccl. vij. c and iij. a</note>Honoure thy father from thy whole harte / ande forgett not the ſorrowfull
<pb facs="tcp:27933:15"/> trauayle that thy mother had with the. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that thou waſt borne thorowe them / ande howe canſt thou recompenſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that they haue done for the?<note place="margin">Tobi. iii e</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Holde thy mother in honoure all the dayes of thy lyfe.<note place="margin">Tobi. iiii a</note> For thou oughteſt to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membre / what ande howe great parelles ſhe ſuffred for the in hyr wombe.</p>
                     <p>My ſonne / care ande bewyſe / ſo ſhall thyne harte proſper in the waye.<note place="margin">Prouer. 23</note> Let not thyne harte be gelous to followe ſynners but kepe the ſtyll in the feare of the Lorde all the daye lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.<note place="margin">Prouer. 22</note> Kepe no company with wine bibers and riottous eaters of fleſh / for ſoch as be dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kards a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d riotours ſhall come to pouerte / ande he that is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to moch ſlepe / ſhall go with a ragged coate.</p>
                     <p>Geue eare vnto thy father that begatte the / and deſpiſe not thy mother whan ſhe is olde.</p>
                     <p>The lorde will haue the father honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the children / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d loke what a mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do / he wil haue it kept.<note place="margin">Eeccel. iiii Exod. 20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Deut. v <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Who ſo honoureth his father his ſynnes ſhalbe forgeuen him a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he that ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noureth his mother / gathereth treaſure
<pb facs="tcp:27933:16"/> to gether. Who ſo honoureth hys father ſhall haue ioye of his owne children / and whan he maketh hys prayer he ſhalbe hearde.</p>
                     <p>He that feareth the lorde / honoureth his father and mother / and doth them ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice / as it were vnto the lorde hym ſelfe. Honoure thy father in dede / in worde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in all pacyence / that thou mayſte haue his bleſſyng / for the bleſſyng of the father / buildeth vp the houſes of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but the mothers curſe / rooteh oute the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacions.<note place="margin">Geneſ. xxvi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. deut. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> iij</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>My ſonne / make moche of thy father in his age / and greue him not as longe as he lyueth. And if his vnderſtanding faite / haue pacience with him / and deſpiſe him not in thy ſtrength. He that forſaketh his father / ſhall come to ſhame / ande he that defieth his mother as curſed of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. xix. d</note>He that hurteth father / or ſhutteth ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te his mother / is a ſhamefull ande an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſonne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Leuit. xix.</note>Thou ſhalt riſe vp before a graye head / and ſhalt geue reuerence vnto the aged.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:16"/>
                     <head>Howe the Maſter a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maſtres ought to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des theyr / ſeruauntes.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>He that delycately bringeth vp his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt from a chylde ſhall make hym hys maſter at length.<note place="margin">Prou. xxix.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whereas thy ſeruaunt worketh tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / intreate hym not euell / nor the hyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge that is faithfull vnto the.<note place="margin">Eccl. vij. c</note> Loue a dyſcrete ſeruaunt as thine owne ſoule.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:17"/>
                     <p>The fodder / the whippe ande the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den belongeth vnto the aſſe / meate correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and worke / vnto the ſeruauntte.</p>
                     <p>If thou lett thy ſeruaunt labour / thou ſhalt find reſt / but if thou let him go Idel / he ſhall ſeke lyberte.</p>
                     <p>The yoke a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the whippe bowe downe the necke / but tame thou the euel ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with bandes and correction.</p>
                     <p>Set hym to worke / for that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him and becommeth hym well.</p>
                     <p>If he be not obedient / bind his fete / but do not to moch vnto hym in any wyſe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without diſcretion do nothing.</p>
                     <p>If thou haue a faithfull ſeruaunt / let hym be vnto the as thine owne ſoule / for in bloude haſt thou gotten hym / if thou entreateſt him euel / and kepeſt him harde / he will ronne awaye from the.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Col. iij. c</note>Ye maſters / do vnto your ſeruauntes that whyche is iuſt ande equall / ande knowe that ye alſo haue a maſter in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">theſ. 6. a. eccle. 33. d Collo. ij. c</note>Ye maſters / put awaye your threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges / and knowe that theyr GOD / is your God alſo / neyther is there any reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb facs="tcp:27933:17"/> of parſones with hym.</p>
                     <p>Be not as a lion in thyne owne houſe / deſtroying thy houſholde folkes / and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſynge them that are vnder the.</p>
                     <p>Who ſo euer worketh any thynge for the / Immediatly gyue him his hyre / and loke that thy hyred ſeruauntes wagis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne not by the ouer night.<note place="margin">Tobi. iiij. c Deut. 24. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The workemans labour ſhall not by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with the / vnto the mornyng.<note place="margin">Leuit. 19. c Tobi. iiij. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that defraudeth the labourer of his hyre / is a bloudeſheader.<note place="margin">eccl. 33. d Deut. 24. c eccl. vij. c</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe ſeruauntes ought to be haue themſelues in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> or lordes. Dames or maſtreſſes.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:18"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Timo. vi.</note>Let as many ſeruauntes as are vnder the yoke / counte theyr maſters worthy of all honoure / that the name of God and his doctrine be not euell ſpoken of.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>Se that they which haue beleuing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters / deſpoſe them not / for they are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren / but rather do them ſeruice / for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche as they are beleuing / and beloued / and partakers of the benefyte.</p>
                     <p>Ye ſeruauntes / be obedient vnto your
<pb facs="tcp:27933:18"/> bodely maſters in all thinges / not with eye ſeruice as men pleaſers / but in ſyngle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of hart fearinge God.<note place="margin">Col. iij. e Epheſ vj. a Tit. ij. b i. Petr. ii. c</note> Whatſoeuer ye do / do it hartely / euen as vnto the lord / and not vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And be ſure / that of the lord ye ſhall receiue the rewarde of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce / for ye ſerue the lord Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Ye ſeruauntes be obedient vnto your maſters / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pleaſe them in all thinges / not anſwering them againe / neyther be ye pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers / but ſhewe all good faithfulnes / that in all thinges ye maye do worſhippe vnto the doctrine of God oure Sauioure.<note place="margin">Tit. ij a Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>j. a Col. iij. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ye ſeruauntes / obeye your maſters with all feare / not onely if they be good a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d curteous / but alſo / though they be frowar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. For that is grace / if a man for conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towarde God endure grefe / and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre wronge. For what praiſe is it / if whan ye be buffeted for your fautes / ye take yt paciently? But if whan ye do well ye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre wronge / and take it paciently / that is grace wyth God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The duety of maryed menne towarde their wyues.
<pb facs="tcp:27933:19"/> The duety of maried menne towardes theyr wyues.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. vij. c</note>Departe not from a diſcrete and good woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that is fallen vnto the for thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in the feare of the lorde. The gifte of her honeſte is aboue golde.</p>
                     <p>If thou haue a wife after thyne owne minde / forſake her not / but committe not thy ſelfe to the hatefull.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. ix. b</note>Vſe thy ſelfe to liue ioyfully with thy
<pb facs="tcp:27933:19"/> wyfe whome thou loue it / all the dayes of thy life (which is but vaine) that god hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vnder the ſonne / all the dayes of thy vanitie / for that is thy porcion in this lyfe / of all thy laboure ande trauaile that thou takeſt vnder the Sonne.<note place="margin">Mark. vj. b Prou. v. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ye huſbandes / loue your wiues / euen as chriſt loued the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and gaue him ſelfe for it / to ſanctifie it / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d clenſed it in the founteine of water by the worde / to make it vnto him ſelfe a glorious congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation / hauing no ſpotte nor wrinkle / nor any ſoch thing / but that it ſhuld be holy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without blame.<note place="margin">Ephe. v. c Gal. 2. c Tet. 3. a. i. Petr. iij. c</note> So ought me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue their wiues / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as their owne bodies. He that loueth his wife / loueth him ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Who ſo euer putteth awaye his wyfe (except it be for fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) cauſeth her to breake matrimonie.<note place="margin">Math. v. a</note> And who ſo euer ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rieth her that is deuorſed / breaketh wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke.<note place="margin">i. Pe. v. iij. i. Teſſ. iiij.</note> Ye men / dwell with your wiues accordinge vnto knowleadge / geuing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure vnto the wife / as vnto the weaker veſſell / and as vnto them that are heyres with you of the grace of lyfe / that youre prayers be not let.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:20"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Num. xxx. Deu. xxiij.</note>If any man make a vowe vnto the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / or ſweare an othe / ſo that he bynde his ſoule / he ſhall not breake his woorde / but do all that is proceded out of his mouth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The duetye of marryed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towardes theyr huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Epheſ. d. c Col. iij. c i. Petr. iij. a</note>Let the women ſubmytte them ſelues vnto theyr huſbandes / as vnto the lorde. For the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is the wiues head / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as
<pb facs="tcp:27933:20"/> Chriſt alſo is the head of the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and he is the ſauiour of his body.<note place="margin">Cor. xj. a</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the congregatyon is in ſubiection of Chryſt / lykewyſe let the wyues be in ſubiection to theyr huſbandes in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
                     <p>Ye women / be ſubiect vnto your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes / that euen they whiche beleue not the woorde / maye without the woorde be wonne by your conuerſatyon / whan they beholde your conuerſation in feare.<note place="margin">i. Petr. iij. a 1. Cor. xj. a Epheſ. v. c Col. iij. c. 2. Tim. 2. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whoſe apparell / ſhall not be outwarde wyth broyded heare / and hanginge on of gold / or in putting on of gorgious araye / but lett the inwarde man of the harte be incorrupt wyth a meke ande a quiet ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite which before GOD is moche ſet by. For after this maner in the olde time / dyd the holy women whyche truſted in God / tyer them ſelues / and were obedient vnto theyr huſbandes / euen as Sara obeyed Abraham and called hym Lorde.<note place="margin">Gene. xviij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let the women aray them ſelues in co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> apparel with ſhamefaſtnes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te behaueour / not wyth broyded heare / or gold / or pearles or coſtly araye / but with
<pb facs="tcp:27933:21"/> ſoche as it becommeth women that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe godlineſſe thorowe good workes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. xiiij. epheſ. v. c</note>Let the woman learne in ſcilence with all ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Suffer not a woman to teache nor to haue auctoritie ouer the man / but for to be in ſcilence. For Adam was firſt formed / ande then Eue / Adam alſo was nor deceaued / but the woman was decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / ande hathe brought in the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.<note place="margin">Heneſ. iij. c</note> Notwithſtanding thorowe bearing of children ſhe ſhalbe ſaued / if ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in faith / and in loue / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the ſanctifying with diſcretion.</p>
                     <p>Let your wiues kepe ſcilence in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation / for it ſhal not be permitted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to ſpeake / but to be vnder obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / as the lawe ſaith. But if they will lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne any thinge / let them axe their huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des at home. For it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not women to ſpeake in the congregation.</p>
                     <p>A man ſhalbe lord a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ruler in his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the woman ſhalbe ſubiect to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Num. xxx.</note>If a maried woman make a vowe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d if ſhe haue letten go out of her lippes a bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ouer her ſoule / and her huſbande heare
<pb facs="tcp:27933:21"/> it / and holdeth his peace therat / the ſame daye that he heareth it / then her vowe and bonde wherwith ſhe hath bounde her ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe ouer her ſoule / ſhall ſtande in effect.</p>
                     <p>But if her huſbande forbidde her the ſame daie that he heareth it / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the vowe low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that ſhe hath vppon her / and the bande alſo that ſhe hath letten go oute of her lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ouer her ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſtate of matrymony in generall.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. xix. a Geneſ. ij. d</note>In the beginninge God created man and woman / for this cauſe ſhall a man lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue father ande mother / ande cleaue to hys wife. And they two ſhalbe one fleſh / now are they not tweyne but one fleſh. Let no man therfore putt a ſonder whyche God hath coupled together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Cor. vij.</note>To avoide whoredome / let every man have his owne wife / and let every woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have her owne huſband / let the man geue vnto the wyfe due benevolence / lykewyſe alſo the wife vnto the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The wife hath not power ouer her owne bodye / but the huſbande / and lykewiſe the man hath not power ouer hys owne body but the wife.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Tob. vj. d and vij. a Ioel. ij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Wythdrawe not your ſelues one from an other / excepte it be with the conſent of bothe / for a tyme / that ye maye geue your ſelues vnto faſtinge and prayer / and then come to gether againe / leaſt ſathan temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te you for your incontinencie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Hebr. xiij. a</note>Let wedlocke be had in price in all poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / ande leet the chamber be vndefyled. For whorekepers and aduouterers God wyll iudge.</p>
                     <p>The Lorde fauoureth man ande wife
<pb facs="tcp:27933:22"/> that agre well together.<note place="margin">Eccl. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. and xi. d Eccl. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Happie is the man that hath a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wyfe / for the nombre of his yeares ſhalbe double.</p>
                     <p>A woman ſhall not ſeparate her ſelfe from her huſbande / but if ſhe ſeparate her ſelfe / that ſhe remayne vnmaried / or be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſyled to her huſbande.<note place="margin">i Cor. 7. d</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>A woman that is in ſubiection to the man / is bounde vnto the lawe whiſe the man lyueth / but if the man die / then is ſhe lowſed from the lawe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth the man.<note place="margin">Rom. dij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <note place="margin">Math. v. d</note> If ſhe be with an other man / while her ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liueth / ſhe ſhalbe called a wedlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kbreaker. But if the man be dead / then is ſhe free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe / ſo that ſhe is no wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke breaker / if ſhe be with an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſtate of Vyrgyns.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:23"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Cor. vij. a</note>I ſaye to them that are vnmaried / and to widdowes (ſaieth S. Paule) It is good for them that they abyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> alſo as I do.<note place="margin">i. Tim. v. b</note> But if they can not abſtaine / let them mary / for it is beter to mary / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to burne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Cor vij. c</note>As concerning virgins / I haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the lorde / neuertheles I ſaye my good meaninge / as I haue obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mercy of the lord to be faithfull. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe it is good for the preſent neceſſite / for it is good for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to be. Arte thou bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vnto a wyfe ſeke not to be lowſed. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:27933:23"/> thou lowſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wife / ſeke not a wife.</p>
                     <p>If a damſel make a vowe vnto the lord / while ſhe is in her fathers houſe / and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d her vowe or ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ouer her ſoule / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to her fathers eares / ande he holde his peace therto / then all her vowes ande bandes that ſhe hath bounde hir ſelfe with all ouer her ſoule / ſhall ſtande in effect.<note place="margin">Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſtate of Wyddowes.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:24"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>imo. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. ij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Cor. j.</note>She that is a ryght widdowe / and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate / putteth her truſt in God / and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth in prayer and ſupplication night and daie. But ſhe that liueth in pleaſures / is dead / euen yet alyue.<note place="margin">Gala. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. b</note> A wyddowe muſt be without blame. But if ther be any that prouideth not for his owne / and ſpeciallie for them of his houſhold / the ſame hath de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyed the faith / ande is worſe then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydell.<note place="margin">i. Petr. ij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Tim. v. b</note>Let no widdowe be choſen vnder thre ſcore yere olde / ande ſoche one as was the wyfe of one man / and well reported of in good workes / if ſhe haue brought vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren well / if ſhe haue bene harbarrowes / if ſhe haue waſſhed the ſaintes fete / if ſhe haue miniſtred vnto them which were in aduerſyte / if ſhe were continually geuen to all maner of good workes.<note place="margin">i. Petr. iiij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger wyddowes refuſe. For whan they haue begonne to waxe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonne againſt Chriſt / they wyll mary / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge their dampnation / becauſe they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue broken the fyrſt faith. Beſydes this they are ydell / and learne to ronne aboute from houſe to houſe. Not onely are they
<pb facs="tcp:27933:24"/> ydell / but alſo tryflynge and buſybodyes / ſpeakinge thinges which are not comly.</p>
                     <p>The vowe of a widdowe / ande of her that is deuorced / all that ſhe bindeth her ſelfe withall ouer her ſoule / ſhall ſtande in effecte vppon her.<note place="margin">Num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortacion to the Ryche of this worlde.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>If riches encreaſe / ſett not your harte vppon them.<note place="margin">Pſal. lxj. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. xiiij. a</note>It becommeth not a couetous man a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a nigarde / to be riche / ande what ſhulde a niggarde do with golde? he that with all his carefulnes heapeth to gether vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſly / gathereth for other folkes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d an other man ſhall make good chere with his goodes. He that is wicked vnto him ſelfe howe ſhulde he be good vnto other men? Howe can ſeche one haue any pleaſure of his goodes? There is nothing worſe / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when one diſfauoureth him ſelfe and this is a rewarde of his wickednes. If he do any good / he doth it not knowing therof / and againſt his wyll / and at the laſt / he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth his vngraciouſnes.<note place="margin">Prouer. 17 Eeccl. iij a</note> A nigard hath a wicked eye / he turneth a waye his face / and deſpiſeth his owne ſoule. A couetous mans eye hath neuer ynough in the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of wickednes / vntill the tyme that he wyther away / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue loſt his own ſoule.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">eccl. xiiij. b eccle. iiii a Tobi. iiii. b Luk. 16. b</note>A wicked eye ſpareth bread / and ther is ſcarcenes vppon his table. My ſonne do good to thy ſelfe of that thou haſt / ande geue the lord his due offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges. Do good vnto thy frende before thou dye / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy abilite reache oute thyne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:27933:25"/>
/ and geue vnto the poore.</p>
                     <p>A rich man ought to ſubmitte him ſelf / and not to reioyſe in his goodes.<note place="margin">Iob. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Charge them whiche are riche in this worlde / that they be not proude / nor truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in the vncerteine riches / but in the liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g God (which geueth vs abundauntly all thinges to enioye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) That they do good that they be riche in good workes / that they giue and diſtribute with a good will / gatheringe vp treaſure for them ſelues / a good foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / againſt the time to come / that they may laye hande on eternall lyfe.<note place="margin">i Timo. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">Math. 6. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gyue almes of thy goodes / and turne neuer thy face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore for almes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuffreth not the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to come in darkenes.<note place="margin">Tobi. iiii b</note> A great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte is almes before the hye God / vnto all them that do it.<note place="margin">Geneſ. iij</note> Let neuer pride haue rule in thy minde nor in thy worde for in pride bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne all deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Eccll. iij.</note> Happie is the riche that is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de without faute / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he that turneth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right waye for golde / neither putteth his truſt in money or treaſure.</p>
                     <p>Go to nowe ye ryche menne / wepe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d howle on your wredchednes that ſhall come vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you.<note place="margin">1. Timo. 6.</note> Your riches are corrupt / 
<pb facs="tcp:27933:26"/> your garmentes are moath eaten. Your golde and your ſiluer are cancred / and the ruſt of them ſhalbe a witnes againſt you: and ſhall eate your fleſh as it were fyre / ye haue heaped treaſure to gether in your laſt dayes.<note place="margin">Leu. ix. c Deut. 24. c Toby. iiij. c</note> Beholde the hyer of the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers whiche haue reped your owne feldes (which hyer is of you kept backe by frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) crieth / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the cries of them which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue reaped / are entred into the eares of the lorde Sobaoth.<note place="margin">Luke xv. c</note> Ye haue lyued in pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re on the aerth and in wantonnes / ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue condempned and haue killed the iuſte / and he hath not reſyſted you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ccle. x. b</note>There is nothing worſe them a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous man. What prideſt thou the / O thou aſſhes? There is not a more wicked thing then to loue moneye. And why? ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che one hath his ſoule to ſelle / yet is he but a fylthy dounge while he liueth.</p>
                     <p>Although the Phiſitian ſhewe his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe neuer ſo longe / yet in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion it goeth after this manner / to daye a king / to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe dead. For whan a man dieth he is the heyre of beaſtes / ſerpentes ande wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:26"/>
                     <p>Wo be vnto the proude welthy in Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to ſoche as thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſo ſure vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mount of Samaria.<note place="margin">Amos vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Luke vi c</note> Which hold / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues for the beſt of the world / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rule the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> houſe of Iſraell euen as they lift / beholde / is the border of the land of the philiſtines wider then yours? Ye are taken oute for the euell daye euen that ſitte in the ſtole of wilfulnes / ye that ligh vppon beddes of yuorie / and vſe your wantonnes vppon your couches / ye that eate the beſt lambes of the flocke / and the fatteſt calues of the droaue / ye that ſynge to the lute / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge of inſtrumentes compare your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vnto Dauid / ye that drinke wine out of gobblettes / ande anointe your ſelues with the beſt oyle / but no man is ſory for Ioſeps hurte.<note place="margin">Iob. xxi. b E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ay v. b i. Reg. xvj. d</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who ſo truſteth in his riches / ſhal periſh.<note place="margin">Prouer. xj. Pſal. xl. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for the lorde ſhall deliuer him in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of trouble.</p>
                     <p>See that ye gather you not treaſure vppon earth / where ruſt and mothes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte / and where theues breake through and ſteale.<note place="margin">Math. vj c Luke xij. d Eccl. 39. b</note> But gather you treaſure toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:27933:27"/> in heauen / where nether ruſt nor mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes corrupt / ande where theues nether breake vp nor yet ſteale.<note place="margin">Pro. xxiij a Luke xij. c</note> For where you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re treaſure is / there is your harte alſo / ye can not ſerue God and Mammon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luke xv. a</note>Make you frendes with the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Mammon / that whan ye ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nede / they maye receaue you into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euerlaſting tabernacles.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Tim. vi. b Prou. 23. a</note>All they that wilbe riche / fall into tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and ſnare / and into many folyſh a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d noyſome luſtes / whiche drowne men in deſtruccion and dampnation. For coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſnes is the roote of all euell / which whyle ſome luſted after / they er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the fayth / and tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled them ſelues wyth many ſorrowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortacyon to the poore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke and impotent Parſones.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:27"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirite / for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>5. a Luke vj. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>All the dayes of the poore are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / but a quiet harte is as a continuall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt.<note place="margin">Prouer. 15</note> 
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. xxxvj</note> Better is a litle with the feare of the lorde / then great treaſure.</p>
                     <p>Better is the poore that liueth Godly / then the blaſphemer that is but a foole.<note place="margin">Pro xix. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>A poore man leading a Godly lyfe / is<note place="margin">Pro. xxvij. a</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:27933:28"/> better then the riche that goeth in frowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. xxxvj. Pro. xv. b Eccl. xxix. d 1. Tim. vj. b</note>A ſmall thinge that the rightuous hath is better then great riches of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. The lorde knoweth the dayes of the Godlie / and their inheritaunce ſhall endu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re for euer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. ix</note>The lorde is a defence for the poore / a defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the time of trouble. For the lord forgetteth not the complainte of the pore.</p>
                     <p>The lord ſhall deliuer the poore from the mightie / and the wretched and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pore ſely people / which haue no helpe.</p>
                     <p>The lord will not forget the poore / the paciente abiding of ſoche as be in trouble ſhall not periſh for euer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. xxj. b</note>He ſhalbe fauourable to the ſimple and poore / he ſhall preſerue the ſoules of ſoche as be in aduerſite.</p>
                     <p>He ſhall deliuer their ſoules from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torcion and wronge / and deare ſhall their bloude be in his ſight.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. 21. a Exod. v. b</note>The prayer of the poore goeth out of the mouth and commeth vnto the eares / and his vengeaunce (or defence) ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and that haſtelie.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:28"/>
                     <p>A ſymple man which laboureth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth / is better then one that is gorgious and wanteth breade.<note place="margin">Pro. xij. b Eccl. 10. d</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou arte the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s helpe (o lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) a ſtrength for the nedeful in his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyté.<note place="margin">Eſay. xxv. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou art vnto him a defence againſt euell wether / ande a ſhadowe againſt the heate.</p>
                     <p>The poore ſhall not alwaye be oute of remembraunce / the pacient abiding of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as be in trouble ſhall not periſh for euer.<note place="margin">Pſal. ix</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The lord ſhall kepe the ſimple folke by theyr right / defende the children of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and puniſh the wrongeous doers.<note place="margin">Pſal. lxxj. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The poore fely people couet water / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they can get none / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue is waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drie for thruſt.<note place="margin">Eſaye xij.</note> I the lord ſhal heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I the God of Iſraell will not forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                     <p>Hath not God choſen the poore of this worlde / which are riche in faith a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d heires of the kingdome which he promiſed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue hym?<note place="margin">Iacob. ij. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The poore that wanteth ſtrength / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath great pouerte / <note place="margin">Eccl. xj.</note> the eye of GOD lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:27933:29"/> vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to good / ſetteth him vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his low / eſtate and lifteth vp his h ade.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to the artificer or handycraftes man.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Geneſ. iij</note>In the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou rate thy breade / tyll thou be turned agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto aerth whence thou arte taken.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. v. a</note>Man is borne to labour / like as the byrde for to flye.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:29"/>
                     <p>An ydle hande maketh pore / but a quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke labouring hand maketh riche.<note place="margin">Prouer. x. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who ſo gathereth in Sommer / ys wiſe / but he that is ſlougyſh in harueſt / bringeth hym ſelf to confuſyon.</p>
                     <p>In all thy workes be dyligent ande quicke / ſo ſhall there no ſycknes happen vnto the.<note place="margin">eccle 31. c Roma. xij. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be not proude to do thy worke / ande deſpayre not in the tyme of aduerſyte.<note place="margin">eccl x. d</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who ſo is ſlouthfull and ſlacke in his labour / is the brother of hym that is a waiſter.<note place="margin">Pro. xviij. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Slouthfulnes bringeth ſlepe / and an ydle ſoule ſhall ſuffre hunger.<note place="margin">Pro. xix. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The deuiſes of one that is diligent / bringe plentuouſnes / but he that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed / commeth vnto pouerte.<note place="margin">Prou. xxj. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that laboureth not / ſhall not eate.<note place="margin">ij. Teſſ. iij.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>A man ſhall goo forth to hys worke / and tylle hys lande vntyll the eueninge.<note place="margin">pſal. 103. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt eate the laboures of thyne owne handes / ſo ſhall it go well with the / and thou ſhalt be bleſſed.<note place="margin">pſal. 127. a</note> Thy wife ſhalbe as a frutefull vyne vppon the walles of
<pb facs="tcp:27933:30"/> thy houſe. Thy children like the oliue braunches rounde aboute thy table. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus ſhall the man be bleſſed that feareth the lorde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">eccl. v. b Iob. x. c</note>A labouring ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlepeth ſwetelie / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be litle or moche that he eateth / but the aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the riche wyll not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to ſlepe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. 23. a Iere. xvij. b</note>Take not ouer great trauayle and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure to be riche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. xix. a</note>A labouring man that is geuen vnto dronkennes / ſhall not be riche.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. x b</note>Delyte not thou in ſlepe / leaſt thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto pouerte / but open thyne eyes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou ſhall haue breade ynough.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">eccl. xxxij. b</note>All that a man eateth ande drinketh / yea / what ſo ſoeuer a man enioyeth of all his labour / the ſame is a gifte of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to Religious or deuoute Parſones.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:30"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>Pure deuocion and vndefiled before God the father / is this.<note place="margin">Iaco. 1. c</note> To vyſit the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les and widdowes in theyr aduerſite / and to kepe him ſelfe vnſpotted of the world.</p>
                     <p>If any man amonge you ſeme deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and refraine not his tongue / but decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his owne harte / this mannes deuocion is in vaine.</p>
                     <p>The feare of the lorde is the right god ſeruice that preſerueth and iuſtifieth the harte / and geueth mirth and gladnes.<note place="margin">eccl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:31"/>
                     <head>Exhortacion to the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">prou. xx. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>It is nought / It is nought ſaith the byer / but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath it / he doth praiſe it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">prouer. xi. a</note>A falſe balaunce is an abhomination vnto the lorde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Leuit. xix.</note>Deale not wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gfully with thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour / with metyarde / weight or meaſure.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:31"/>
                     <p>Whan thou felleſt ought vnto thy neighbour / or byeſt any thynge of hym / deceaue nor oppreſſe him not.<note place="margin">Deut. xxv. Leuit. xix b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt not haue in thy bagge two maner of weyghtes / a great and a ſmall. Neyther ſhalt thou haue in thy houſe diuers meaſures / a great a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a ſmall / that thy lyfe maye be longe in the lande / which the lord thy God ſhall geue the / for who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s an abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacion vnto the Lorde thy God.</p>
                     <p>God knoweth both the deceauer / and hym that is deceaued.<note place="margin">Iob. xij</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:32"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. xij.</note>Who ſo tilleth his grounde ſhalbe fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with breade.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prouerb. xj</note>Who ſo hoordeth vp his corne / ſhalbe curſed among the people / but bleſſing ſhal lyght vppon his head that ſelleth it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Deu. xxiiij. Leuit. 19. c</note>Whan thou haſt reaped downe thyne harueſt / and haſt forgotten a ſhefe in the felde / thou ſhalt not turne again to fetche it / but it ſhalbe for the ſtraunger / the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles and the widdowe / that the lorde thy God maye bleſſe the in all the workes
<pb facs="tcp:27933:32"/> of thy handes.</p>
                     <p>In like caſe when thou haſt plucked thine oliue trees and viniarde.</p>
                     <p>Whan thou reapeſt thy la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / thou ſhalt not reape downe the vtermuſt borders of it rounde aboute / nor gather it all clene vp.<note place="margin">Liuit. xix. c Deut. 24. d</note> Euen ſo likewiſe thou ſhalt nor pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thy viniarde clene alſo nor gather vp the grapes that are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe / but ſhalt leaue them for the poore and ſtraungers / for I am the lorde your God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to Souldiours or menne of warre.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. x a</note>Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou goeſt oute to bataile againſt thine ennemies and ſeeſt horſes and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectes of the people more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou / be not a trayde of them.</p>
                     <p>Nowe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are come nigh vnto the battaile / the prieſt ſhall ſteppe forth / ande ſpeake to the people / and ſaye vnto them. Heare (o ye people) ye go this daye into the battayle againſt your ennemies / let not your harte faint.<note place="margin">Deut. xii c Num. xiiij. 2. Marc iiij. Deut. 28 a</note> Feare not / be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde of them. For the lorde your God goeth with you to fight for you agaynſt your ennemies / that he maye ſaue you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Numer. xxj</note>Whan thou commeſt nygh vnto a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to fyght againſt it / thou ſhalt offre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peace. But if they wyll not deale peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wyll warre with the / then beſiege it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Deu. x <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Whan thou muſt lighe a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſeaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a citie / againſt the which thou makeſt warre to take it thou ſhalt not deſtroy the trees / nor heawe them down with the axe for thou mayeſt eate of the frute / for it is but woode vppon the felde / and no man / ande can not come ande be bulwarkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the. But the trees that thow kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt
<pb facs="tcp:27933:33"/> that men eate not of / thoſe ſhalt thou deſtroye / and rote oute / and make bulwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes therof / againſt the citie that warreth with the / tyll thou haue ouercome it.</p>
                     <p>Let hym that is a fearde ande fainte / turne home againe.</p>
                     <p>It is a ſmall matter for mannie to be ouercome with fewe / yea / ther is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the God that is in heauen / to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer by a great multitude or by a ſmall companie / for the victorie of the battel ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth not in the multitude of the hooſt but the ſtrength commeth from heauen.<note place="margin">i Mach. iiiv i Reg. xiiij</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ye Souldiours do no man wronge / and be content with your wages.<note place="margin">Luke. iij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to Cuſtumers Tolners and Publicanes.</head>
                     <p>Ye Cuſtumers a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ners / require no more of the people the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is appointed you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation to Lombar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and vzurers.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:34"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Leu. xxv. exod. xxij. c Deut. xxiij Ezech. 18. a</note>If thy brother waxe poore / and fall in decaye beſyde the / thou ſhalt receaue hym as a ſtranger / or geſt / that he may lyue by the / and thou ſhalt take no vſurie of him / nor more then thou haſt geuen / but ſhalt feare thy God / that thy brother maye liue beſides the. For thou ſhalt not lende hym thy money vppon vſury / nor deliuer hym thy meate vppon advauntage.</p>
                     <p>Let no man take vſurie of his brother.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:34"/>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt occupie no vſurie vnto thy brother / neither with money nor with fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / ner with any maner of thinge that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury maye be vſed withall / that the lorde thy God maye bleſſe them all that thou takeſt in hande.<note place="margin">Deu. xxiij. Exod. xxij. Leu. xxv.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whan one of thy brotheren is waxed poore / in anye citie within thy lande / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the lorde thy God ſhall geue the / thou ſhalt not harden thine harte / nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe thyne hande from thy poore bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but ſhalt open thine hande vnto hym and ſende him / according as he hath nede.<note place="margin">Deut. xv. a 1 Ioh. vij. c</note> Beware that there be not a pointe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall in thine harte / that is / thinke not that he ſhall not geue it the againe.<note place="margin">Rom. x. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> For if thou lokeſt not frendly vppon thy brother / and giueſt him nothing then ſhal he crye ouer the vnto the lorde / ande is ſhalbe counted ſynne vnto the. But thou ſhalt giue him. For becauſe of it / ſhall the lorde thy God bleſſe the in all thy workes / and in all that thou putteſt thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto. The la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhall neuer be without poore / therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I the and ſaye / that thou open thine han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto thy brother / whiche is nedy ande
<pb facs="tcp:27933:35"/> poore in thy lande.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. xxiiij</note>If thou lende a poore bodie (ſaith god) thou ſhalt not lye downe to ſlepe with his pledge / but ſhalt delyuer hym his pledge againe whan the Sonne goeth downe / that he maye ſlepe in hys owne raiment / and bleſſe the / ſo ſhall the ſame be rekened vnto rightuouſnes / before the lorde thy God.<note place="margin">Pſal. xiiij. a</note> Lord (ſaith Dauid) who ſhall dwel in thy tabernacle? Who ſhall reſte vppon thy holy hyll? He that ſweareth vnto his neighbour and diſapointeth him not. He that geueth not his money vpon vſurie / and taketh no rewarde againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ezec. xviij.</note>If a man be Godly ande do the thinge that is equall and right / he greueth no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die / he geueth his detter his pledge again / he parteth his meate with the hungrie / he clotheth the naked / he le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth nothing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vſurie / he withdraweth his hand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doyng wronge / he handleth faithfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d man.<note place="margin">Math. xxv. Pſal. xiiij. a</note> This is a rightuous man / he ſhall ſurely lyue / ſayth the Lorde God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>h. xxij</note>Thou haſte receaued gyftes to ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:27933:35"/> bloude Thou haſt taken vſurie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Thou haſt oppreſſed thy neighbours by extorcion / ande forgotten me / ſayth the lorde God.</p>
                     <p>He that hath pitie vppon the pore / len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto the lord / and loke what he laieth oute / it ſhalbe paide him againe.<note place="margin">Pro. xix. c</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortacion to Whooremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Fornicatours.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prouerb. v. Prou. vij. a</note>The lyppes of an harlotte are a drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping honycombe / and her throte is ſofter than oyle. But at the laſt ſhe is as bitter as wormewoode / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as ſharpe as a two-edged ſwerde. Her fete go downe vnto de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ath / and her ſteppes pearſe thorowe vnto hell. She regardeth not the path of life / ſo vnſtedfaſt are her wayes that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not knowe them. Heare me therfore (O my ſonne) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d departe not from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of my mouth. Kepe thy waye farre from her / ande come not nygh the doores of her houſe. That thou moorne not at the laſt (when thou haſt ſpent thy bodye and goodes) and then ſaye. Alas / why ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I nurtoure? Why did my harte deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe correccion? Wherfore was not I obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto the voyce of my teachers / ande harkened not vnto them that enfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. v c Iob. 31. a</note>My ſonne / why wylt thou haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in an harlot and embrace the boſome of an other woman? For euerye mannes wayes are open in the ſight of the lorde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he pondereth all their goinges.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. 23. c</note>The mouth of an hariot / is a depe pit / 
<pb facs="tcp:27933:36"/> wherin he falleth that the lorde is angrie wythall.</p>
                     <p>A foliſh reſtleſſe woman / full of woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / and ſoche one as hath no knowledge / ſytteth in the doores of her houſe vppon a ſtoole aboue in the citie / to call ſoche as go by / and walke ſtrayght in their wayes.<note place="margin">Prou. ix. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who ſo is ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (ſaith ſhe) ſet hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come hither / and to the vnwyſe / ſhe ſaith ſtolen waters are ſwete / ande the breade that is priuelie eaten / hath a good taſte.</p>
                     <p>But they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder not that death is the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and that her geſtes go downe to hell.</p>
                     <p>He that loueth harlottes / ſpendeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye that he hath.<note place="margin">Pro. xxix. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Turne awaye thy face from a beauty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman and loke not vppon the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes of other.<note place="margin">Eccl. ix. a Mat. v. c</note> Many a man hath periſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thorowe the beautie of women / for thorowe it / the deſyre is kindled as it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a fyre.</p>
                     <p>A whoore is a depe graue / and a harlot is a narrowe pytte.<note place="margin">Prou. xxiij Proue. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> She lurketh lyke a thefe / and thoſe that be not a ware ſhe bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnto her.</p>
                     <p>Let vs not committe whooredme as
<pb facs="tcp:27933:37"/> ſome of them did / and fell in one day thre and twentie thouſand.<note place="margin">i. Cor. x. a</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Teſſ. iiij. Epheſ. iiij. Toby. vj. d Rom. i. e</note>The will of God is / that ye ſhulde ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from whooredome / that euery one of you ſhuld knowe howe to poſſeſſe hys veſſell in holines and honour / and not in the luſt of concupiſcence / as the heathen / which knowe not God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ephe. i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. c Math. xij d</note>Let no fylthie communication procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de oute of your mouth / but that which is good / to edify withall. And greue not the ſpyrite of God / wherwith ye are ſealed vnto the daye of redemption.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Flee whoordome. All ſinnes that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth / are without the bodie. But he that committeth whooredome / ſynneth agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt his owne bodie. Knowe ye not that your bodie is the Temple of the holighooſt? Whome ye haue of GOD / ande are not your owne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. d. c i. Cor. vj. b</note>Aduouterers / whooremongers / forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catours a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnclene parſons / ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heret the kingdome of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ierem. v. d</note>Shulde I then (ſaith the lorde) for all this haue mercy vppon the? Thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue forſaken me / ande ſworne by them
<pb facs="tcp:27933:37"/> that are no Gods. And albeit they were bounde to me in mariage / yet they fell to aduourrie / and haunted harlots houſes.</p>
                     <p>In the deſyre of vnclenly luſte / they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re become lyke the ſtoned horſe / euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neieth at his neighbours wife.<note place="margin">Ezech. xxi Ierem. ix.</note> Shulde I not correct this / ſaith the lorde? And ſhuld I not be auenged of euery people that is lyke vnto this?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation vnto dronckardes.</head>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:38"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. xxj. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Wo be vnto them that ryſe vp earlye to vſe them in dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet at night are more ſupperfluous in wine. In who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe companies are harpes and lutes / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>abret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and pipes. But they regarde not the worke of the lorde / and conſyder not the operation of his handes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. iij. a</note>Wo be vnto them that are conning me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuppe oute wyne / and experte to ſet vp dronkennes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. xxiij.</note>Where is wo? wher is ſorrowe? where is ſtrife? where is brawling? where are woundes without cauſe? where be reade eyes? Is it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> amonge thoſe that be euer at the wine / and ſeke oute where the beſt is / and occupie them ſelues to drinke oute g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s glaſes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cuppes? Loke not thou vppon the wine howe read it is / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what colour it is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glaſſe. It goeth doun ſoft<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie / but at the laſt it biteth like a ſerpent / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtingeth like an Adder. And when a man is dronk / he caſteth his eyes vnto ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge women / ande dothe muſe vppon fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 21. c Rom. 13. b</note>Take hede vnto your ſelues / that your hartes be not ouerladen with exceſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:27933:38"/> eating and with dronkennes.</p>
                     <p>Wyne is maruelous ſtronge and ouer commeth them that drinke it / it deceaueth the minde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bringeth both the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the kinge to dotage a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vanite.<note place="margin">iii. Eſdras ij Prou. xx. a</note> Thus doth it with the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dman a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with the free / with the poore and riche. It taketh awaie their vnderſtanding and maketh them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reles and merie / ſo that none of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth any heauines / dette or duetie. It cauſeth alſo a man to thinke that the thinge which he doth / is honeſt and good / and remembreth not in what auctorite he is / and that he ought not to do ſoche thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Moreouer whan men men are drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge / they forget all fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip / all brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faythfulnes and loue. But as ſone as they are dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken / they drawe oute the ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde / and will fight. And whan they are laide downe from the wine / ande ſo ryſen vp againe / they can not tell what they did.</p>
                     <p>Wyne is a voluptuous thinge / ande dronckennes cauſeth ſedicion / who ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteth therin / ſhall neuer be wyſe.<note place="margin">Prou. xx. a Ephe. b. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be not thou a wyne bebber / for wyne hath deſtroied many a man.<note place="margin">Prou. 21. a Epheſ. v. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:39"/>
                     <p>O howe well content is a wiſe man with a litle wine? The fyre proueth the harde yron / euen ſo doth wine proue the hartes of the proude / whan they be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">eccle. xxxjd Prou. xxxj. 1. Timo. 5.</note>Wyne ſoberly dronken / quickeneth the life of man. If thou drinkeſt it meaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly / thou ſhalt be temperate. Wyne was made from the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glad (and not for dronkennes) Wine meaſura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly dronken / is a reioycing for the ſoule and body.</p>
                     <p>But if it be dronken with exces / it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth bitternes and ſorrowe vnto the min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. Dronkennes fylleth the minde of the fooliſh / with ſhame ande ruine / dimy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſheth the ſtrength / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maketh wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ephe. v <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Be not droncken / for therin is exceſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortation vnto all ſynners generally.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ezech. xviij Deut. xiiij. 4. Reg. 14.</note>The ſame ſoule that ſineth / ſhal die. The childe ſhall not beare the fathers offence / nether ſhal the father beare the childes of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence.
<pb facs="tcp:27933:39"/> But the rightuouſnes of the rightu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous ſhalbe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the wickednes of the wicked ſhalbe vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf alſo.<note place="margin">ii. Para. 25. Iere iii. 18. a</note> But if the vngodly will turne awaye from all his ſynnes that he hath done / and kepe all my commaundementes / and do the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that is aequall a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d right / doutles he ſhall liue ande not dye. And I will thinke no more vppon all his ſynnes that he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.<note place="margin">ezech. 18. a</note> For I haue no pleaſure in the death of a ſynner (ſaith the lord God) but rather that he conuert and lyue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A generall exhortation vnto all men.</head>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt reprehend thy brother whan he ſynneth / leaſt his offence come ouer all.<note place="margin">Leuit. 19. c</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be ye all of one mynd / one ſuffer with an other / loue as bretheren / be pitifull / be curteous.<note place="margin">i Petr. iij. b</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Recompenſe not euel for euell / neyther
<pb facs="tcp:27933:40"/> rebuke for rebuke / but cotrary wiſe / bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / and knowe that ye are called therto / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that ye ſhuld be heires of the bleſſinge. For who ſo liſteth to liue / and wolde fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſee good dayes / let him refraine his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from euell / and his lippes that they ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke no gile.<note place="margin">Geneſ. xii Math. xv.</note> Let him eſchue euell / ande do good. Let him ſeke peace and enſue it. For the eyes of the lorde / are ouer the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous / and his eares are open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their prayers. But the face of the lorde beholdeth them that do euell.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:40"/>
                  <p>A right good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly rule howe all faithfull chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhall occupie and exerciſe them ſelues in their daily prayers.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>¶Luke. xxij. Math. vj. ¶</bibl>
                     <l>Chriſt teacheth vs in his Goſpell ſaying.</l>
                     <l>Praye that ye fall not into temptation.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at Ippeſwych by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryſhe. Anno. 1548.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:41"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Howe a man ſhall behaue him ſelfe in the morning when he ryſeth.</head>
                     <p>When thou riſeſt in the morninge / loke that thou with all humblenes of minde / knele downe / ande lifting vp thy harte / thy handes ande thyne eyes into heauen / vnto God the father almightie / praie on this manner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:41"/>
                     <head>The prayer for the morning.</head>
                     <p>O Almyghtie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mooſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle God we thanke the for the ſwete ſlepe and comfortable reſte / that thou haſt geuen vs this night. And for as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as thou haſt commaunded by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde / that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be ydle / but all waies occupied i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertuous exerciſes / eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to his calling. We moſt humbly beſeche the / that thine eyes maye attend vppon vs / dayly defende vs / in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ſuccour vs / cheriſh comforte ande gouuerne all our councels / ſtudies and la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours. In ſoche wiſe that we maye ſo ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de this daye / according to thy mooſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will / without hurtinge of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour / that we maye diligentlie and ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye eſchue and auoide all thinges that ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de diſpleaſe the / ſet thy alwayes before ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eyes / liue in thy feare / and euer worke that that maye be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de acceptable before thy diuine Maieſte / vnto the praiſe of thy mooſt holye name / through Ieſu Chryſt our lorde. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:42"/>
                     <head>An other prayer for the Mornyng.</head>
                     <p>SEeyng that thou (O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) act that one ande alone al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God / which art in euerie place / beholdeſt the councels / deuiſes and workes / yea / the very thoughtes of all men / and geueſt to euery one according to theyr dedes. We beſeche the that (for as moche as thou haſte mooſt graciouſlye preſerued vs this night) we may not ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this daye after oure owne minde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (which is alwaies euell and wicked) but earneſtly loke vppon / and dyligentlye followe thy fatherlie wil / thine euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel / thy healthful worde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re which is alwaies good / parfect a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d holie / and fulfyll the ſame with good harte / that thy diuine name may alwayes be ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tified / both nowe and euer of vs miſerable ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners through thy derely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne Ieſus chriſt our lorde and Sauiour So be it.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:42"/>
                     <p>Afther that thou haſt praied on this maner (ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that we be all ſinners) it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be expedient (if thou haſt conuenient lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therunto) to confeſſe thy ſelfe on this maner vnto God the father.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The confeſſyon of our ſynnes vnto God the father.</head>
                     <p>O Almightie God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d heauenlie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / maker of heauen and earth / I confeſſe my ſelfe vnto the / euen from the very harte / that I am a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / wretched and abhominable ſynner.</p>
                     <p>Ande haue wickedlie tranſgreſſed all thy holy commaundementes / and the diuine preceptes of thy Godlie will. The ſynnes (alas which I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in my fleſh againſt the) are ſo great and ſo excedingly encreaſed / that they are no leſſe innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the ſandes of the ſea. And they thruſt me downe euen as an intollerable burden. In theſe wicked ſynnes (oh lorde God) haue I hitherto walked according to the wil of the prince of the world / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les I dyd that that was pleaſaunt to the
<pb facs="tcp:27933:43"/> fleſh ande euell luſtes / thorough vayne thoughtes / the blindnes of my harte / the outwarde pretence of Godlynes and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned faith. This came to paſſe (Ah wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that I am) becauſe that I dyd neuer aerneſtly ſtryue againſt the ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Sathan / nor the concupiſcences or deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the world / nor yet the luſtes of my fleſh. But fylthilie obeied them a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tymes more / than the admonicions of thy holie ſpirite. O lorde my God. It ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to paſſe alſo / that I dyd ſet nought by thy Godly counſell / deſpiſed thy holie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / and feared thy vengeaunce and heauy diſpleaſure nothing at all. But what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I haue in this behalf offended thy mooſt Godly maieſte / it ſore repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth me / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the faulte greueth me eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harte. And if it were not (o mooſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father) that thou haddeſt layde vp mercy in the bowelles / bloude a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonne ande our lorde / for ſo manie as vnfainedly repent and trulie beleue be their ſynnes neuer ſo great and manie / I ſhulde ſee none other waye / but throwe my ſelfe downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb facs="tcp:27933:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> (through deſperation) into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomles pit of hell. But for as moche as thou haſte ſett thy welbeloued ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt / to be our mediatour and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſtocke. And haſte promiſed grace / mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and forgiuenes of ſynnes to as many as aſke it in his name / through faith in his bloude. Therfore in this tyme of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and mercye / I myſerable ſynner come nowe vnto the / ande deſire the my lorde God that thou wilt graunt me / thorowe that our lorde Ieſus Chriſt / a right ande true faith. And for his ſake / forgiue me all my ſynnes / and make me to walke dayly more and more in a newe harte / and in the frutes of the holy ghooſt / that I maye vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpiſe all the vngodly luſtes of this worlde / and that I maye be founde conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent / pure of liuing temperate / good righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous / honeſt / diligent in all goodnes / me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / mercifull / modeſt / humble and ready to forgiue ſoche as offend me / euen from the very harte. And ſo lyue all the dayes of my lyue accordyng to thy dyuine wyll and true feare.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:44"/>
                     <p>That I maye die to the world / to all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and to my ſelfe. And with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence and mery harte / loke for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge of the lorde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte. To whome with the and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghooſt / be all honour ande glorie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer. So be it.</p>
                     <p>Thou mayeſt (if thou wilt) after thy confeſſyon / ſaye the lordes prayer called the Pater noſter. And ſo (commending thy ſelfe vnto God) fall to ſome honeſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vertuous exercyſe / according vnto thy cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling. But what ſo euer thou doeſt / do it with purenes of harte / and with ſyngle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of eye. Yea ſo do it / as though God were preſent / and loked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the / as vndoubtedly he doth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer to be ſayde when thou goeſt to bedde.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:44"/>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>O God the almightie lord / by who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ordre ande wyll the night ande darknes do nowe approche / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in we ſhal giue our ſelues to quiet and ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe. We mooſt inſtauntly deſyre the / that thou graciouſly receaue vs into thy tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ande kepinge / that the prince of dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes do not hurte vs with his terrous and feares. And although we muſt ſlepe / becauſe of oure feblenes / yet let oure harte
<pb facs="tcp:27933:45"/> and minde wacche vnto the. Go thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs / and ſhewe vs the waye as a piller of fyre / that we maye followe the ſo well in reſt / as in buſynes ande occupations of this lyfe. And graunt that we be not founde in thy ſyght / children of nyght a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d darkenes / but of daye and lyght / through Ieſus Chriſt our lorde. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>An other Prayer.</head>
                     <p>THys our mortall body / whiche through ſynne daylye decayeth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diminiſſheth / muſt at the laſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether periſh a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d become earth / wherof it is come and made a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then ſhall our vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / whiche we through our owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce / haue made vnto our ſelues / take an ende. But mooſt mercifull creatour and maker of all thinges / vouchſafe ſo to breake / deuide and dyſſolue me / thy poore creature who am gathered / knyt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the / and graunt that I maye alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes haue in minde / thy diſſolution / and of whome I am knit together / hauing an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye to what place I muſt go to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that
<pb facs="tcp:27933:45"/> I / not being prepared / be no brought without nuptiall or brydall garment / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy iudgement ſeate. For like as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daye is ones paſt / we giue our ſelues to reſt / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo muſt we / this life being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / reſt in the death. Nothing is more ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto life / then the daye / ande nothing more like vnto death / then the night. And nothing ſo lyke the graue or ſepulchre as the couche bedde or bedſteade. Thus / good keper a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all euell / grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs / nowe lying in impotencie and feble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / of our ſelues / that / through the / we maye be preſerued this night from all the aſſaultes of the deuell of hell.</p>
                     <closer>AMEN.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Whan thou goeſt to thy labour or worke.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Prayer.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:46"/>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <p>O Mooſt kinde and gentle heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father / thou knoweſt / and haſt alſo taught vs / howe great the weakenes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is / ſo that man (without thy Godly helpe) can do nothing. Thus vouchſafe to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs thy holie ſpirite / that he may ſtrengthen / ſtirre ande moue our vnderſtanding and reaſon / in all thinges that we this daye outwardely ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute and take in hande / or of that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie
<pb facs="tcp:27933:46"/> ſhall thinke or haue in minde / to the intent that it may all be done to thy glorie / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the proffyt of our neighbour. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Whan a man is bounde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes anye Iourney.
<figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Prayer.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:47"/>
                     <p>THys our lyfe / moſt mercifull lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / is nothing els but a pilgrimage and through fare / for we haue here no abyding or dwelling place. We are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me from the / and we muſt returne agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto the. But amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt or betwene all the trappes / aſſaultes / pittes and ſnares which the deuell hath laide oute and ſpred abrode / for vs / blinded in ſinne / vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe thou / o lorde Ieſu Chriſt / to leade vs with thy righthande / for thou art a true / truſtie / and ſure frende. Open our eyes / to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we miſſe not the way whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch thou thy ſelfe art but leade vs / through a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by thy ſelfe vnto the father / to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that al we may be made one with the and him / euen lyke as thou arte one with him.</p>
                     <p>O mooſt mercifull lorde / lyke as thou doeſt ſende thy holy Anngels to be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of as manye as ſerue ande pleaſe the with a ſymple / innocent ande pure harte / by the which / they be ledde / lyke yong chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are ledde of them which are elder and ſtronger than they. And like as thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vouchſafe to ſende thyne A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngell. Raphaell / to be a guide vnto the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:27933:47"/> of that reuerent man Toby / vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe euen ſo / o lorde / to ſend vs the ſame A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngell / although we are not ſo worthy / as the ſame Toby was / that he maye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and leade vs through that way / whych is not pleaſaunt vnto vs / but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the. So be it—</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Whan a man commeth home or at his iourneys ende.
<figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Thankeſgiuing and prayer.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:48"/>
                     <p>I Thanke the / o heauenly father / for thy great grace and mercy / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou haſte ſhewed vnto me / in going forth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in returning or comming againe through thy holy bleſſyng / whiche thou geueſt vnto all them that kepe thy holy worde and do therafter. Graunt us / o gracious God / here / where we haue no abiding or dwelling place / a pure a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d quiet conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / through thy ſonne Ieſus chriſt who is our onely reſt. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>For Kinges Princes and Rulers.
<figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <pb facs="tcp:27933:48"/> Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Lorde of lordes Ieſus Chriſte / thou art an exempel and glaſſe or myrrour of them which gouuerne and beare rule of Realmes / countreis a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cities / whome they ought to followe / for thou art the beſt and the wyſeſt / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore canſt thou not erre / nor do ony other thinge but wel. Vouchſafe with the light of thy clerenes and wyth the fyre of thy lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue / to kindle the hartes of al ſoch / as thou / through thy Godlye prouidence / haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ordeined to be rulers ouer the people / to the intent that they through the as through or by a foregoing light / maye ſee / and perceaue what is beſt to be done / and fulfill the ſame / and that they / taking thy alwayes for a ſure marke of their eye / do not that thinge whiche onelye ſemeth good in their ſyght / but that which maye be to thy honour / to our proffyt ande to their health a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſaluacion / to thintent alſo / that they maye iuſtly and duelye miniſter and execute thir offyce / geuen vnto them
<pb facs="tcp:27933:49"/> of the / ſo that we with them a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they with vs may leade a peaceable / vertuous ande quiet lyfe. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>For all teachers and Prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers of the mooſt holie worde of God.
<figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Prayer.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:49"/>
                     <p>O mercyfull prieſt / chefe Biſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ande true good hearde Ieſus Chriſte vouchſafe / through thy holie ſpirite / to ſtrengthen all preachers and teachers which thou haſt called ande ſent to be labourers in thy holy harueſt / for to breake and diſtribute the breade of thy holy worde to thintent that they may boldely a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d earneſtly ſet their ſoules in the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy holy word / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for their ſhepe / agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt all the threatni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs and falſe entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes of the raueni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wolues a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes / which go about to ſeduce a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bring vs oute of the right waye / for their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſake / through their falſe doctryne.</p>
                     <p>To the intent that they may ſo teache a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d declare vs thy holy lawes and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / that we maye be taught and edified / and that alſo thy Godly honour may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more ande more be magnifyed therby. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>For all them which lye in the extreme panges of death / or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe.
<pb facs="tcp:27933:50"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Pytyfull Phiſitian ande healer both of ſoule and body / Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu. Vouchſafe to caſt thyne eyes vppon thy poore ſynnefull creature. N. who lieth here captiue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bounde with ſic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knes / turning his weakenes to thy glorie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his health. And vouchſafe / good lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / to ſend him pacient ſufferaunce / that he maye ſtedfaſtly contynue to the ende / and that he maye with a true ande parfet
<pb facs="tcp:27933:50"/> fayth / fyght manfully againſt all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the deuell when he maye no longer continue. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>For all wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bound with the Lordes bandes.
<figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Prayer.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:51"/>
                     <p>GOd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>harted Lord Ieſu chriſt Lyke as thou diddeſt comforte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d delyuer thy dyſciples and all elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and choſen holie men and women in all their nede / martirdome a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d paines which they ſuffred of the tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes wrongfully / and diddeſt alſo cure ande heale them of theyr woundes / paines and ſmarte / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe hope of the crowne of euerlaſtinge lyfe. Euen ſo vouchſafe (thou which arte a helper of all them that call on the in all trouble a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nede) to deliuer this pore wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke veſſell / whiche is here bounde with a frute after thyne owne ſymilitude and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes (notwithſtanding that ſhe hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in tranſgreſſyng of thy holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement / to bring forth her children in paine and woo) that ſhe maye be made a glad and ioyful mother / through the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we creature with good ſpede / that the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de maye haue name and Chriſtendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / and that the mother may be purifyed to thy honour and to hyr health. So be it.</p>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                        <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:51"/>
                     <head>Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Good father a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d geuer of all good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / God almightie / we (poore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wormes of the earth) labour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d take paines / digge and delue / til a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d plowe / plante and ſowe / and can do no more.</p>
                     <p>But thou onelye mayeſt ande wylt geue the encreaſe in due time. Therfore moſt beſt / yea / onelye good father a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d God / vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſafe (through thy deuyne prouidence) to preſerue ande kepe all the frutes of the earth / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuffer the ſame to growe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to a parfect grouth / although we are not worthy of it but for thy names ſake / to thintent we may vſe them to our neceſſyte and ſuſtinaunce / with thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuing / and alwayes to thy glorye. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:52"/>
                     <head>A generall confeſſyon.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. iii. Gene. vi. and .iii. v.</note>O Lorde God almightie / father of mercy and God of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>force / we thy pore creatures reſort vnto the knoledging and confeſſyng our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy glorious maieſtie / that we all are greuous ſynners ande can of our ſelues do nothinge but ſynne. For all our yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacions / intents a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thoughtes are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and deſpoſed vnto euyll from oure youth vp.<note place="margin">O ſee. xiii. ii. Cor. ii. Philii. ii. Gene. iii. Epheſ ij. Pſ. l. lxij. Iohn xv. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a. lxiii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Iere. xiij.</note> Oure dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth of our ſelues / we of our ſelues are not able to thinke a good thought. It is thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie that doſt worke in vs both the will a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the dede. We are but earth and naturally the children of wrath. We of our ſelues are but vaine / yea / lighter then vanitie it ſelf / We ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothing without the. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is not one of vs whole / we are all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane / and al our rightuouſnes is but as a fylthy cloth. We haue no more power to do good of our ſelf / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a blacke Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Inde hath powr to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his ſkin / or the Leopard hir ſpottes. Now acordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to this euil a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d corrupte in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ination of our
<pb facs="tcp:27933:52"/> nature ſo haue we liued I thought / word / and dede.<note place="margin">Denie. ix</note> We haue ſynned / we haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / we haue gon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> backe from thy lawe / and haue not harkened vnto thy word.</p>
                     <p>we haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> loued the (O lorde our god) with all our herte with all our ſoule / with all our ſtrength and with all our power. We haue bene fore tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſours of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. We haue nor put our who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le truſt and confydence only in the. We ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue in our troubles a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nede / not ſought for helpe onely in the. We haue not called one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vpon thy name / but with falſe confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / with vain ſuperſticion / and vnlaufull othes haue we blaſphemed thy name. We haue praid a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d made interceſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and ſtones / and made thy creatures our aduocates ande mediators contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to thy word. We haue repoſed our truſt and affiance in our owne dedes and in ſuche workes as haue bene deuiſed by mens fantaſyes beſydes thy ſcripture.</p>
                     <p>We haue wandered on vaine pylgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / offering vp money / candels ande ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to ymages and relikes with ſuche li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſuperſticion. We haue bene ſlothfull in
<pb facs="tcp:27933:53"/> our buſynes. We haue not bene feruent a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diligent in doing of our dutye. Specially on ſuch dayes as be appointed for the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of thy worde / we haue not plied our ſelues wholly to lerne it / nor occupied our tyme in praier a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thankes vnto the.</p>
                     <p>And as touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the loue that we ought to haue vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy ſake we haue not bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earneſt in at al times. We haue not loued our neyghbours as our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues / we haue not done / as we would be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto / we haue bene vnge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle / vnpacient / vncurteous froward / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diſpleaſed. We haue reioyſed in our neyghbours hurt and bene ſory of his welfare. We haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ledde with falſe doctrine a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d errours fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the way of thy truth / We haue ſinned with our fathers / we haue done amiſſe / we haue dealt wykedly.<note place="margin">Pſal. xvj.</note> Therfore our moſt deare father which arte in heauen / for as muche as we haue blaſphemed the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not ſought alway the glory of thy name / graunt now that from henſeforth thy name maye be ſanctified ande hallowed in vs / Graunte nowe that thy kingdome maye come / and that in ſteade of ſinne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d errour / thou one-</p>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:53"/>
                     <head>To praye.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Grace a fore meate.<note place="margin">Rom. xiii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>I knowe (ſaieth the Apoſtle) and am full certyfied in the lorde Ieſu / that ther is nothinge vncleane of it ſelffe / but vnto him that iudgeth it to be vncleane / to him it is vncleane. But if thy brother be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ouer thy meate / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> walkeſt thou not now after charite. Deſtroye not with thy meate / him for whome Chriſt dyed.</p>
                     <p>O oure father which art in. etc.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace a fore meate.</head>
                     <p>Let not oure treaſure therfore be euell ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of.<note place="margin">Rom. xliij.</note> For the kingdom of God is not meate and drinke / but righteouſneſſe and peace / and ioye in the holy Gooſt.</p>
                     <p>O oure Father which are in. etc.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace a fore meate.</head>
                     <p>Meate doth not further vs vnto God.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vij.</note> If we eate / we ſhal not therfore be the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / If we eate not we ſhall not therfore be the worſe. But take hede that this you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re libertie be not an occaſyon of fallinge to the weake.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace a fore meate.</head>
                     <p>Meate hath God created to be recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes of them which beleue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d knowe the trueth.<note place="margin">ij. Tim. iiij.</note> For euery creature of
<pb facs="tcp:27933:54"/> God is good / ande nothinge to be refuſed that is receaued with thankeſgeuing / for it is ſanctifyed by the worde of God and prayer.</p>
                     <p>O oure Father which art in heauen. etc.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Receaue youre meate without grudgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / </l>
                        <l>Take hede ye neuer abuſe the ſame / </l>
                        <l>Geue thankes to God for euery thinge / </l>
                        <l>And all waye prayſe his holy name.</l>
                        <l>Who ſo doth not / is ſore to blame / </l>
                        <l>No euell enſample ſe that ye gyue / </l>
                        <l>Thus doth Goddes worde teache yow to lyue.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cori. iij.</note>Whatſoeuer ye do in worde or dede / do all in the name of oure Lord Ieſu Chriſt / giuinge thankes vnto God / the Father by hym.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:54"/>
                     <head>
                        <figure/>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Grace after meate.</head>
                     <p>Thankes be vnto the O lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtie (mooſt deare Father of heauen) for geuinge vs oure foode in due ſeaſon / for openinge thy mercifull hande / ande for fyllynge vs with thy ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tefull bleſſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. And we beſeche the for thy ſonnes ſake Ieſu Chriſt / not onely to preſerue vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from abuſynge of the ſame / but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:27933:55"/> to lende vs thy grace / that we may euer be thankefull vnto the therfore. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace after meate.</head>
                     <p>Thankes be vnto the O lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie (mooſt deare father of heauen) for certifyeng vs by thy bleſſed word / that all kindes of meates are cleane. And we beſech the lende vs thy grace / that we may alwaye thankefully receaue the ſame / not onely without ſuperſticion or ſcrupuloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té of conſcience / but alſo without greuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or offendinge our brethren / And ſo to walke in the waye of godly loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite / that with oure meate we neuer deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troye him / for whome thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt dyed as well as for vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace after meate.</head>
                     <p>Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be vnto the O God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (mooſt deare father of heauen) for ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge vnto vs thy bleſſed worde / whiche is oure treaſure / oure pearle / yee and oure riches / more precious then eyther golde or precious ſtone. And we beſeche the / though corporall meate and drinke be no parte of thy kyngdome / yet ordre thou vs ſo in receauinge the ſame / that we neuer
<pb facs="tcp:27933:55"/> geue occaſyon of ſlaundringe thy worde / or offendinge the weake. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace after meate.</head>
                     <p>Thankes be vnto the O lorde God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie (mooſt deare father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) for layenge vp oure ſaluacion onely in thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not in anie kinde of meate. And we beſeche the / gide vs ſo in the vſe therof / that we may followe ſuch thinges as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke for peace / and wherby we may edifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne an other. And neuer to geue vnto the weake anye occaſion of fallinge from thy worde. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Grace after meate.</head>
                     <p>Thankes be vnto the O lorde God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie (mooſt deare Father of heauen) for ordeininge thy creatures to be meate / foode and ſuſtenaunce vnto oure bodies / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haſt ſanctified the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by thy bleſſed word / etc? We beſeche the / make vs ſo to increace in ſtedfaſtneſſe of thy faith / in perfecte knowledge of thy trueth / and in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of feruent praier vnto the that to vs alſo they may be ſancryfyed and holy / and that we may euer both tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckfully receaue them / and vertuouſly vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to the good enſample of other. amen.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27933:56"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. 50. d.</note>Bleſſed is he that exerciſeth him ſelfe in theſe thinges. And who ſo taketh ſoch to hart ſhalbe wyſe. If he do theſe thinges / he ſhalbe ſtrong in all. For the light of the lorde leadeth him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 13. b.</note>Yf ye knowe theſe thinges / bleſſed are ye if ye do them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luke. 12. e. Iacob. 4. b</note>The ſeruaunt that knoweth his Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wyll ande doth it not / ſhalbe beaten with manie ſtripes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2. c</note>But he that fulfylleth the worde of God / abideth for euer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 20. d</note>Theſe thinges are written to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we ſhuld beleue / that Ieſus chriſt is the ſonne of God / and that we thorowe hym / might haue life euerlaſting. Which the chefeſt goodnes voutchſafe to geue vnto all them that ſhall ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare / ſee or rede this preſent lytle booke. AMEN.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:57"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27933:57"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
